[SPEAKER_00]: I thought of doing some proper vipassana, as in the interrogation, self-interrogation, that obviously, as we spoke before, results... can result, if done rightly, in establishments of the mind, in samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, the proper vipassana of self-interrogation would bring forward samādhi, kompoccha, upon the right themes, wholesome themes, themes free from greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think previously, the one we've done before, it was kind of about suffering, wasn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling and suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I thought, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I know we can do the one in terms of... well, in terms of the unwholesome, in terms of sensuality or in terms of ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, again, like, it can be done by anyone, to oneself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for example, right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there... is there sensuality present in the background of your mind, in any shape or form?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there the desire, or the desire for the wanting of some pleasure based upon the senses?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: By the way, I can...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not just asking you.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm putting the question out and I'll also describe whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, yeah, you can say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there a desire for wanting a pleasure on a kind of sense basis?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is what saṃsāra is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I entertain a possibility that somehow... Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would be the further.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: For now, is there... is there a desire for pleasure of the senses?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes or no?
[SPEAKER_00]: Just the most generally.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to look for every little what-if.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just overall, is my mind now
[SPEAKER_00]: Under the pressure of sensuality, or is my mind now not under the pressure of sensuality?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the question a person should be asking oneself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, because I'm sitting in a comfortable position.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maintaining it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but I'm trying to maintain that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever there's a
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but avoiding this comfort is not sensual.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not necessarily sensual.
[SPEAKER_01]: Trying to maintain the comfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasure of sensuality is basically pleasure that you can gain through the sense bases engaging with its sensual counterparts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Greed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you lustful about sitting in a comfortable chair?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have an option, you are... you're sitting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes it gets uncomfortable in this position.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not like... that's when it's like... you have to start differentiating the type of pleasure that is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because often people can't... can't see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So often people will, like, assume you must forsake everything, everything, every little desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are desires that are not desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: Avoiding discomfort is just intentional for an arahant as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I mean lust, aversion, delusion, sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there any, as the Buddha would say, like, desire in regard to the world, or sort of displeasure in regard to the world, which is rooted on the same domain, discontent, craving for...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the question a proper vipassana can start with.
[SPEAKER_00]: In my mind, right here, right now,
[SPEAKER_00]: Under the pressure of sensual craving, of wanting, the wanting of pleasure, pleasure of the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the answer will have to be yes or no.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that general level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is my mind currently affected with sensuality, as Satipaṭṭhāna Sutta would say?
[SPEAKER_01]: As far as I can tell, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the answer, like, let's start, let's say the answer is no.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, I'm not completely sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how probably many people would answer it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no, but I'm not completely sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does not being completely sure mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: It means you're not free from doubt in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you're not free from doubt in regard to a dhamma, a phenomena, you can't say you're free from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't say you're free from that domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where freedom from doubt, for a Sotāpanna, is like the first step towards the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's the same principle, then, that he can develop... Like, Sotāpanna is not free from sensuality, for example, because he's still not free from doubt in regard to sensual domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereas the Buddha would say he still hasn't fully understood the gratification, the danger and the escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: You understand that fully means you fully went beyond doubt in regard to the nature of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a fine starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can say, no, currently, my mind is not under the influence of sensuality, but I'm not completely sure about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, does that mean that there might be a way that sensuality is influencing you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does that mean there might be a way that sensuality might influence me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's more like it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically, you recognize that currently, the mind is not under the pressure of sensuality, but you also simultaneously there, but simply by saying, hmm, I'm not sure, means the possibility of sensuality, you recognize you are not free.
[SPEAKER_00]: There could be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I know what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the point here.
[SPEAKER_00]: To start discerning the possibility of sensuality, that you are still liable to.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that need... like, you can't wait for it to be manifest in the future, to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Possibility, it has to be dealt as possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, if in the future the sensuality manifests, that's not the possibility now that you're thinking of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, it came through the domain of possibility, but at that time, in the future, you're gonna... another domain of possibility in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because possibility is a part of that structural domain of manifested things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that are present and its possibilities.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's implicated.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's what gives things the meaning.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: The possibility of sensuality that you implied through the answer, that one will imply if they say, no, currently I'm not...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not oppressed by sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, I'm not quite sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means, okay, the time will come when I will be oppressed by sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that also means that the reason that I'm not oppressed now is not fully understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I not oppressed now?
[SPEAKER_00]: And why I might be oppressed in the future?
[SPEAKER_00]: With the next one that comes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Understanding that possibility of oppression.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Needs to be done in the present, presently arisen experience that now you're having vipassana about.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you overcome the whole domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the root of the domain, central domain, domain of anger, domain of unwholesome, is not in the particular manifestation of those.
[SPEAKER_00]: The root is you being liable to the possibility of those.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why dukkha,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like... not necessarily the tremendous, horrific torture, pain and discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's this is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dukkha is opposite of sukha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, would be translated as this is, unease.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... that's the nature of human experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not that everybody suffers all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: But possibility in the... all the time in human experience is
[SPEAKER_00]: That's that of uneasiness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is implied.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because things get, at any given moment, in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's a present possibility of things in the future, at any given moment, going not the way you want them to.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha said, fundamentally, suffering is basically being separated from things you want, being united with things you don't want.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, united with feelings and perceptions you don't want.
[SPEAKER_00]: Separated from the ones you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, just misconceiving the five aggregates, misconceiving the experience as a whole, that's why you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you misconceive it as you're the one in control, you're the one in charge.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, every next second, when another thing manifests, it can prove you wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you remain liable to that for as long as you maintain assumption that you're in charge.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you stop at any assumption you're in charge, you have surmounted the domain of possibility of being proven wrong, that you are not in control, on account of which you would suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: The possibilities must be understood as possibilities within the presently enduring experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like momentary glimpses of figuring out or discerning why and how and working some methodical patterns.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a simple question and a simple answer, but you need to know what to look for it and then you get to see the signs of things that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: And is my mind currently pressured with sensuality?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can my mind be then pressured with sensuality?
[SPEAKER_00]: Hmm, maybe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe means yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doubt means yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so my mind can be pressured by sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I have to wait for that in the future to prove that yes, truly, it was pressured?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or I already know that simply by doubting it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You already know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't understand the nature of that possible pressure, you're liable to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's your starting point, by the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Starting point is you're liable to that pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like a perfect satipaṭṭhāna, and then, occasionally, Puthujjana makes mistakes, and then, steps back into sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's Puthujjana, not free from sensuality, because he hasn't understood that domain of possible pressure of sensuality, possible liability.
[SPEAKER_00]: If liability is possible, means, overall, you are liable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not always, but sometimes, and sometimes, it's enough for the nature of sensuality to still pertain to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't want nature of sensuality to still pertain to you, or nature of doubt, or nature of suffering, or nature of anger, or nature of anything unwholesome, that possibility of pertaining to you needs to be understood and abandoned right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: As possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Needs to be discerned.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why we always talk about the peripheral awareness, the mindfulness of, like, the signs, because it's on the level of signs and tokens of the presently manifested things.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in,
[SPEAKER_00]: Currently, presently, mind is not oppressed by sensuality, but it signs its tokens, its significances, that it might be in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what binds you.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact that the mind is currently pressured or not pressured, that's basically a result of your liability to that domain in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you don't need to wait for it to be pressured to know that you are pressured.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to wait for it to realize that you're not in control, like, to be forced upon you through, like, accidents or whatever things happening.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just the fact that it might happen means you're not in control.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you don't need to have anything horrible happen to you in order to become aware of the dukkha, the fundamental sign of human experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it won't be seen on the particular basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already a symptom of your liability.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's get back to the presently...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is a possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a possibility, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now people would generally, like... What the mind would usually do, is try to rationalize it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But finding out why or how, because of this or because of that, it's all the result of your liability in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Buddha meant, hit by the first arrow.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's too concerned about figuring out who hit him.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the name of the client from the man who shot him?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the name of this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Who is the surgeon?
[SPEAKER_00]: What are they?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is relevant is that you were touched in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, you're liable to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, possibility of sensuality is something that the mind is liable to.
[SPEAKER_00]: In this presently enduring experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can let that endure or sink in.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to figure it out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Start recognizing the phenomenon of enduring possibility as a phenomenon of enduring possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is your attitude then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Towards possibility of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: I immediately think I want to be careful.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to be careful, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you want to be careful?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I want... because I want that possibility to become an actuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which you already are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no, like, right or wrong answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through doing this kind of interrogation, you get to clarify and see signs and tokens of presently enduring phenomena, presently enduring dhamma, and then the mind starts to discern them, as also presently enduring dhamma on a more peripheral level.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how the mind gets established upon the right things, upon non-sensuality, non-greed, non-aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, ask yourself then, or whoever listens to this can ask oneself then, why
[SPEAKER_00]: Would I be affected by the possibility of arising, of sensuality arising?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would... Would I be affected?
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how would I clarify that in the present?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like waiting for the thing, but on the level of possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's assume that you would be affected, because in the past you always were affected.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you ask yourself, why am I affected?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why the possibility, right now, right here, right now, possibility of enduring, possibility of arising, of sensuality arising, why am I liable to it, right here, right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's a possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yes, but that's clearly not on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You did not create that possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, what are the characteristics of that possibility?
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's clarify that angle first.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are the characteristics of the possibility of sensuality, presently enduring?
[SPEAKER_01]: They are characteristics.
[SPEAKER_00]: Describe it, just in any manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's bug... it's connected to the body, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely, inseparable from the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Body characteristics.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, something is inseparable from the randomly arisen body, that you have no control over.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no control over your beating heart, over the operating eyes, nose, smell, taste, touch, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is inseparable from it, which means possibility of the sense... sense bases of your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that also implies it's kind of structural as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha said, I wants to go and feed its own domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it does.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a wild animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the five wild animals, their feeding grounds and the possibilities of what they could eat, that's just how things are.
[SPEAKER_00]: You haven't created that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's important thing to discern.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because people might
[SPEAKER_00]: Think it's on them, and then try to prevent this particular thing to be, or that, or interfere with this side to... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, of course, restraint needs to be beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to restrain the animals, in order to understand the nature of the feeding ground, and how it affects you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, the possibility of eye feeding on sights, is the eye's possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Smells, possibility of smells is the nose possibility, possibility of touch, bodily possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why does that possibility then affect you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Only if it's... if I think it is my possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you appropriate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you then appropriate it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the necessary condition for appropriation that the Buddha said?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the necessary condition for regarding something as yours?
[SPEAKER_01]: But... for me, regarding...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, but why would you regard it as for you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would you accept that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, okay, it is for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I come with a gun and a bullet and say, this is for you, would you say, oh, yeah, sure, give it to me, shoot me?
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the pressure of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whenever there is appropriation, there is welcoming beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is perceived pleasurability of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why sense of self, as Yanagira pointed out, is always developed on the basis of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha says, sabhe saṅkhara anicca, sabhe saṅkhara dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to see that which is inseparable from this thing that you are taking as yours, as actually unpleasurable, as not wanted.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, absolutely true.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are affected by the possibilities of sensuality,
[SPEAKER_00]: that actually pertain to your senses, not to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Possibilities are not a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are possibilities.
[SPEAKER_00]: Problem is when you start engaging on account of the possibilities, on account of the pressure of possibilities.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you cannot start engaging with them unless you've taken them as pertaining to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the necessary basis for taking anything as pertaining to you is regarding it as dear, pleasurable, agreeable, non-threatening.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence the Buddha's insistence constantly talking about seeing the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's how you uproot.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't just say, okay, this is not for me anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if still there is the implication of pleasurability of it, the assumption for me is automatic.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you undo the assumption for me, not by saying, okay, it's not for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good luck with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But by actually seeing it as unpleasurable, more fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, automatically, it becomes, oh, not for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the simile of the charcoal pit.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the Buddha said, if the two men, two strong men, would come and grab you by the arms and drag you towards... and drop you in a... like a hole dug up full of embers, wouldn't your mind want to be everywhere else except there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Intention will be turning everywhere else except wanting to go into that hole.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you start regarding the possibility of sensual pleasure like that,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you stop being liable to the entire domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how whatever present, like particularly, actually arises for your eye, nose, smell, taste, touch, and so on, it will not induce the sensual domain upon you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha said the Tāgata still sees, hears, recognizes beautiful things in the world, but he has no desire and lust in regard to them, because he freed himself from the assumption of sensual domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Assumption of my essential domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Assumption of pleasurability of my essential domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, it's just agreeable side, disagreeable side.
[SPEAKER_00]: Agreeable, comfortable chair.
[SPEAKER_00]: Disagreeable, discomfortable chair.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of that is sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of that will be anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of that will be suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of that will be a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all, like, all this
[SPEAKER_00]: Just on a basis of couple of right questions and right attitude in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what vipassana truly is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why we would say, he investigates the meaning, like, to himself, questions himself, or if he sees somebody who might know more, understand more, he goes and gets himself interrogated, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's how you unravel... Yeah, you know these things to some extent, but you really want to discern them on the basis of the present enduring mindfulness of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: And see, all while we talked, nothing has... the basis hasn't changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind is presently not pressured by any sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, but how about possibility of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I fully certain, free from the extent of sensual domain?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know means you're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why aren't you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it doesn't pertain to you, as you just clarified it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It pertains to the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, because I'm still actually regarding it as dear and agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Buddha said you should regard your senses and the mind, I think, in itself as well, like the assassins, like the best friend that, you know, comes and gets your trust and then just wants to kill you at night.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like you go paranoid all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just recognize.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I just need to stop regarding this possibility of sensuality as not my friend.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dangerous, perilous, charcoal pit, burning embers, skin disease, all the similarities you're going to get.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not everything all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Miserable, ugh, hate.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just that degree where you're liable to it, and the possibilities where you're liable to all of it, because of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you stop welcoming that possibility that pertains to the senses, not to you, then that possibility stops bothering you.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are not liable to the possibility of sensuality, can you then be liable to anything that manifests itself through that possibility of sensuality?
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever possibility becomes more possible, like here and now, there might be whatever possible
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you're not thinking about the particular, or future, or this might be possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think about possibility in its nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: As if, currently, I'm not pressured by any sensual cravings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I say that would be the same for the future?
[SPEAKER_01]: Means...
[SPEAKER_01]: But if there is a sensual craving that comes.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a possibility?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not as a possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it won't be a sensual craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you free yourself from the possibility of sensual craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like any particular manifestation of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say, the answer is, I look presently oppressed by sensual craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: The answer is yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, my mind is just thinking about this sensual object.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, based on that, okay, so can you then say that in the future you'll be free from sensuality?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because even now you're not free.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the first step, what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Restrain.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't go for a sensual object.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, now, the pressure of it has been revealed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, same questioning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why, instead of, why would I be pressured in the future, just start with, why am I pressured now?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's...
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a possibility here and now for engaging here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Possibility to engage now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I'm obsessed with cake, so, and there's a cake right in front of me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yesterday, I said, oh, there's a possibility that if I see a cake in the future, I will be pressured to go for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, today, there is a cake in front of me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I've... now, the possibility for engaging with that cake is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if I've surmounted that possibility...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yesterday.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yesterday, I'm still surmounting it today, even if the cake is presented.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the possibility is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: The cake is presented.
[SPEAKER_00]: The possibility is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But your surmounting of the possibility didn't end yesterday.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the possibility is not split.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's present and enduring right here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it was the same possibility that you had in the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: It'll be the same possibility you have in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by surmounting the possibility, you have surmounted your past sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're surmounting any future engagement with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Regardless of what object... You're the one who surmounts the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...correctly sees it presently, he doesn't think in the past, I was, and he doesn't think in the future, I will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because by seeing it correctly, that possibility of mistake of I am right here, right now, he's already... his past is included in it, and the future is included in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they're all subordinate to the presence of that possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind is still not oppressed currently.
[SPEAKER_00]: Possibility of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Possibility of the mind being oppressed by the unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: You could just even stay with that question for a while as well, because it will clarify the domain of the possibility, without overly particularizing it, so to speak, overly rationalizing it, nor mystifying it either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I liable to being affected by the unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't rush answering it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you'll see that what you are thinking about, what you are kind of refraining from an answer to an extent, is the domain you asked about, is the domain that you need to understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: And often, the reason why people don't understand it is because they don't see it, because they never ask the question in the right way, as a way of establishing the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, that's how even jhānas are established.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what Maha Moggallāna, when the Buddha encouraged him,
[SPEAKER_00]: To practice steady his mind in jhānas, because it would be much to his fruit and benefit, he goes under the root of the tree and says, first jhāna, first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the first jhāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the Buddhist scribe, he said, it's this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the presence of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the presence of this factor, or that factor, whatever you translate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he was understanding it, understanding it, he answered it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, can I do more of this?
[SPEAKER_00]: As in further development of the same principle?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Second, third, fourth.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by asking the question, am I liable to the pressure of the unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I liable to the pressure of centrality?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I liable to centrality?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I liable to your will?
[SPEAKER_00]: And not like, yes, no, well, this means that, and over-rationalizing it, or providing psychologizing answers.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just by staying with that question for a while, you're staying with the domain that you directed your question to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you start to discern the domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not jumping to give an answer, but instead, discerning the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: on account of the enduring domain that you asked about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could just... somebody can just spend a day having the mind established upon this question of being liable to unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just spend your day with that being an implication of your day, whatever you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: That unwholesome, you might be liable to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you'll see, when a particular unwholesome arises, you realize, yes, this could have only arisen on the overall liability towards the possibility of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not that that possibility has become this particular one.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, they're two separate domains.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the possibility of my liability to unwholesome states throughout the day,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you get an unwholesome state.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is still a possibility of being liable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's now also verified on the present level.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't... you stop caring about the present level in that direct manner, because you realize that's not where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is on the level of the mind and being affected by the domain of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The domain of possibility of sensuality, of will, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, if you become mindful of the... of your liability towards unwholesome,
[SPEAKER_00]: That in itself, that mindfulness becomes a protection against unwholesome, actually affecting you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might not be completely out of it, but mindfulness of the possibility of unwholesome affecting you, means no particular unwholesome can affect you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness of the fundamental liability to dukkha, means no particular dukkha can affect you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not about removing that... you can't remove that possibility, because it's not yours to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize, all you have to do is develop mindfulness in regard to it, to the extent necessary, whereby you stop entertaining slightest notion that this is pleasurable and for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's often the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: People overshoot the mark.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't see where the problem is, then they overdo it and they end up denying things.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must stop thinking, I must stop looking, I must... blind, deaf man becomes the goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must not do this, I must not do this, I must not do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't know what to do, you start denying everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you must not engage with sensuality or with ill-will on a particular basis, means the body needs to be restrained, speech needs to be restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind needs to be restrained and the restraint of mind is through the restraint of understanding the possibility of being liable to it in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: By you blaming the possibility and trying to get rid of it, means you not seeing where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a person, instead of, like, all this dhamma, stop thinking about it, is impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I is thinking about sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: Animals want to feed, and that's what we say.
[SPEAKER_00]: You tie them in, they'll be thinking about their feeding grounds, where they used to go and eat and do stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not your problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is, why am I emotionally bothered by this, literally?
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: Pressure of sensuality will arise again in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why, or will I, be emotionally affected by that?
[SPEAKER_00]: If the answer is yes, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I emotionally affected by this?
[SPEAKER_00]: And you realize, people would realize that they would be emotionally affected by this, because they never dwelt long enough on the fact that you can't be emotionally affected by it, even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, you can't have it be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: You haven't created it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not bound with you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Its own saṅkharas are its respective senses, inseparable from.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all you need to do is then, oh, all you need to do is stop regarding it wrongly and then it will stop affecting you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you stop regarding it wrongly if you start seeing it, no, this is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how you arrive at that, regarding it as a danger, it's up to a person himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether through simple faith in the Buddha as being ultimately right, knowing what he's talking about, and you already have verified a great deal of it, so you just have faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: What he said himself, it's worth, regarding it as dangerous, it's going to have tremendous benefit.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't quite know how, but I'll do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yeah, that's enough to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That basis of faith, which will then result in knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, if you need more of, like, vipassana and self-questioning, hammering it further, fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're gonna arrive at the same conclusions, because that's what the Buddha did say.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't fabricate, like, a false advertisement.
No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the possibility of sensuality affects a person presently, because he's still
[SPEAKER_00]: He hasn't seen pleasure of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He might have seen how various sensual objects are ugly, repulsive, dissatisfactory, dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he hasn't seen that pleasure in regard to them is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he kept looking on the level of the objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: But pleasure is neither in the sight nor in the eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in regard to the two.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasure of the touch is neither in the that which is touching, the object of the touch, nor your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it needs to be seen for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that pleasure...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's not enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: This pleasure is not... No, it's real.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a real pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you understand the gratification of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you understand that that pleasure is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you rewrite the significance.
[SPEAKER_00]: You rewrite the signs and tokens of central pleasure, which is factual.
[SPEAKER_00]: But instead of dear, agreeable, welcoming, non-threatening, it's seen as threatening, murderous, dangerous, perilous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in order to rewrite those signs and tokens, you need to see it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, you won't be applying it to the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean, like, when the question, when a person, if a person presents a question, so, okay, currently I'm not bothered by any sensuality or real world, but can I be bothered?
[SPEAKER_00]: Will I be bothered?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, maybe, probably.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is a presently recent experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: That probability,
[SPEAKER_00]: And instead of jumping at answer, stay mindful of that peripheral probability.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the domain I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so now I'll go talk, eat, walk, sit, lay down, while probability of being affected by unwholesome still remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you might want to be keen to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you might be keen to solve it.
[SPEAKER_00]: To figure it out, to free yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's good.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what it's not good is when that becomes craving for getting rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That means, ah, you're bound by it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to allow it to exist to its own extent, the possibility of sensuality, not actual engagement with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then stop denying, stop trying to get rid of it, because that's not on you either.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like blaming the things that your dog wants to eat.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the sense wants to eat.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what animals feeds on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just how it works.
[SPEAKER_00]: By you deriving emotional pleasure from engaging with that type of food on account of I, that's on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or emotional dissatisfaction on account of lack of the food for your I, that's on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you develop emotional indifference in regard to the pleasure, in regard to the whole sense domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you free yourself from the sense domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what we spoke before.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stop wanting the wanting of sensual pleasure by your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't stop wanting of your senses directly, because they're not yours to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: You restrain them, sure, to create a basis for the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you stop wanting their wanting,
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you sever your liability to anything unwholesome, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yeah, that possibility of liability, for somebody who has developed his mind in regard to it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it still stays the possibility of sensuality, but the liability is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, you are not li... you went beyond it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The domain of sensuality with possibility remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why arahant can still discern it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he went beyond it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't dismantle the structure of I and the sights, as people would sometimes try to do, which is like a wrong view of a shortcut.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, he went beyond it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the possibility of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he's not liable to engage with it anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, the beautiful sights still remain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sound, smell, taste, touches.
[SPEAKER_00]: Agreeable, disagreeable, comfort, discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: But none of that's central anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he sees the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, he's seen the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's seen the danger in the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he's seen the danger in the pleasure to the extent necessary for that liability to be completely rewritten.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the level of signs and tokens and nimittas of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now, when sensuality arises, there are no nimittas of subha and agreeable, beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are nimittas of this has been despised and abandoned and dangerous and disgusting.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it means now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is general danger, disgust in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: By you being gratuitously bound to the enjoying pleasure of it, you don't see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I'm saying this because whoever would try to practice this, inevitably, the mind would then try to get rid of this possibility, as in, that would be the way of fixing the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: The way of fixing the problem is developing your mind in regard to that possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean, like, sometimes it's good to not even try and answer the question, just formulate it clearly, clearly, and let it endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: First jhāna, first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is first jhāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: Domain of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the domain of sensuality?
[SPEAKER_00]: The liability to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is my liability?
[SPEAKER_00]: Let it endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, there will be a phenomenon that you might want to kind of overly define, but that's not the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is to rewrite the emotional significance of it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, liability of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I'm welcoming it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because fundamentally, I do not see it as the most perilous thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, if you don't even have a notion, not even a peripheral degree of sort of recognition of the liability to sensuality, how can you rewrite anything about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you fully encapsulate it within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's even if somebody lives their life perfectly restrained for the rest of their life, still remain bound with sensuality, because they haven't understood that domain, that liability.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't want to be rewriting the liability, as in the content of your liability.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to be rewriting, basically, your attitude towards the liability.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you rewrite its significance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could say, someone who practices rightly is liable to suffering, but then he ceases to be liable to that liability of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, the body is liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of that, he is liable to.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Arahant says, any disturbance that's left, it's on account of this body, these five aggregates, until they break apart.
[SPEAKER_00]: Disturbance.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the most the suffering can wanna be for an Arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not suffering, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if the mind is developed in regard to jhānas, then even that disturbance won't be perceived.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, clarifying the enduring liability to suffering or sensuality of anything wholesome is not for the sake of getting rid of it, it's for the sake of clarity of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having it endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as long as you're mindful of your liability to sensuality, you cannot possibly engage with sensuality on a particular level.
[SPEAKER_00]: The necessary basis for particular engagement with sensuality is oversight of the liability to sensuality in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it would have meant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impossible to engage with sensuality without having already been bound by sensual perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, discerning the liability of sensuality is already perceiving sensuality on that level of possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are already sensual perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're mindful of them,
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't welcome them, don't entertain them, for as long as they endure, that's all you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a gate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gatekeeper.
[SPEAKER_00]: You then realize, I don't need to go and worry about the particular manifestation of it, because it won't be a problem, because I'm not abandoning this gatepost.
[SPEAKER_00]: My mindfulness, peripheral awareness of the liability to unwholesome.